<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc7991.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="none" submissionType="independent" category="info" version="3">

<front>
	<title abbrev="RTMP Errata and Addenda">RTMP Errata and Addenda</title>

	<author initials="M." surname="Thornburgh" fullname="Michael C. Thornburgh">
		<address>
			<postal>
				<city>Santa Cruz</city>
				<region>CA</region>
				<code>95060-1950</code>
				<country>US</country>
			</postal>
			<email>zenomt@zenomt.com</email>
			<uri>https://zenomt.zenomt.com/card.ttl#me</uri>
		</address>
	</author>

	<abstract><t>

		The specification for Adobe's Real-Time Messaging Protocol
		(RTMP), last updated in December 2012, contains errors,
		omissions, and ambiguities that impede interoperation. This
		memo corrects, clarifies, and amends portions of the RTMP
		specification.

	</t></abstract>

	<note>
		<name>Copyright Notice</name>

		<t>Copyright © 2023 Michael Thornburgh. All rights reserved.</t>

		<t>Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person
		obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation
		files (the "Software"), to deal in the Software without
		restriction, including without limitation the rights to use,
		copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or
		sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom
		the Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following
		conditions:</t>

		<t>The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall
		be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
		Software.</t>

		<t>THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY
		KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE
		WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE
		AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT
		HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY,
		WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
		FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE
		OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.</t>

	</note>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

<t>At the time of writing, Adobe's Real-Time Messaging Protocol (RTMP) continues
to be used by the media streaming industry and in media streaming products
for transmitting video and audio over IP networks, including between and
through various stages of live video production, ingest, and distribution.</t>

<t>The <xref target="RTMP">RTMP specification</xref> was last updated by Adobe
in December 2012. That version contains numerous errors, omissions, and
ambiguities that impede the independent development of correct and interoperable
streaming products.</t>

<t>At the time of writing, the RTMP specification is considered to be an
immutable historical artifact. This memo is intended to be referenced alongside
<xref target="RTMP"/> to correct, clarify, and amend portions of that historical
specification.</t>

<t>This memo addresses RTMP Version 3 as publicly described in
<xref target="RTMP"/>. It does not address private or undocumented extensions
for which interoperation is not desired by the extending parties.</t>

<t>For coordinated interoperable extensions and enhancements to RTMP, see
<xref target="E-RTMP">Enhancing RTMP, FLV With Additional Video Codecs and HDR Support</xref>.</t>

<section title="Terminology">

<t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
"<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
"<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
"<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>"
in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
<xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they
appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

</section> <!-- Terminology -->
</section> <!-- Introduction -->

<section title="Common Syntax Elements">

<t>Definitions of types and structures in this specification use traditional
text diagrams paired with procedural descriptions using a C-like syntax.  The
C-like procedural descriptions <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be construed as definitive.</t>

<t>Structures are packed to take only as many bytes as explicitly indicated.
There is no 32-bit alignment constraint, and fields are not padded for alignment
unless explicitly indicated or described.  Text diagrams may include a bit
ruler across the top; this is a convenience for counting bits in individual
fields and does not necessarily imply field alignment on a multiple of the
ruler width.</t>

<t>Unless specified otherwise, reserved fields <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be set
to 0 by a sender and MUST be ignored by a receiver.</t>

<t>The procedural syntax of this specification defines correct and error-free
encoded inputs to a parser.  The procedural syntax does not describe a fully
featured parser, including error detection and handling.  Implementations
<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include means to identify error circumstances, including
truncations causing elementary or composed types not to fit inside containing
structures, fields, or elements.  Unless specified otherwise, an error
circumstance <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> abort the parsing and processing of an
element and its enclosing elements.</t>

<t>This memo uses the elementary types and constructs described in
<xref target="RFC7016" section="2.1.1" sectionFormat="of"/>.
The definitions of that section are incorporated by reference as though fully
set forth here.</t>

<section title="Additional Elementary Types">

<t>This section lists additional elementary types used in the following
sections.</t>

<dl newline="true">
	<dt><tt>uint24_t var;</tt></dt>
	<dd>An unsigned integer 24 bits (3 bytes) in length, in network
	byte order and byte aligned.</dd>

	<dt><tt>uint16le_t var;</tt></dt>
	<dd>An unsigned integer 16 bits (2 bytes) in length, in little-endian
	byte order and byte aligned.</dd>

	<dt><tt>uint32le_t var;</tt></dt>
	<dd>An unsigned integer 32 bits (4 bytes) in length, in little-endian
	byte order and byte aligned.</dd>

</dl>

</section> <!-- Additional Elementary Types -->
</section> <!-- Common Syntax Elements -->

<section title="Byte Order">

<t><xref target="RTMP" section="4" relative="#4-byte-order-alignment-and-time-format" sectionFormat="of"/>
states that "all integer fields are carried in network byte order". However,
there are two exceptions in the specification where multi-byte integers are
coded in little-endian byte order. To draw attention to these exceptions and
to eliminate the dissonance between the exceptions and the statement, the
first two sentences of that section are amended to read</t>

<blockquote>
Unless otherwise specified, multi-byte integer fields are carried in network
byte order, byte zero is the first byte shown, and bit zero is the most
significant bit in a word or field. This byte order is commonly known as
"big-endian".

</blockquote>

<section title="Chunk Basic Header">

<t><xref target="RTMP" section="5.3.1.1" relative="#5311-chunk-basic-header" sectionFormat="of"/>
describes the one, two, and three byte encodings of the Chunk Basic Header.
The descriptive text gives a formula to decode the three-byte encoding as
though the "<tt>cs id - 64</tt>" field is little-endian; however, this is not
explicitly stated and is easy to miss given the diagrams and the description
of the field as just "8 or 16 bits". This section clarifies the Chunk Basic
Header encodings.</t>

<artwork align="left" type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|fmt|  2 .. 63  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7|0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|fmt|     0     |   cs id - 64  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7|0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7|0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|fmt|     1     |       cs id - 64 (LE)         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

struct chunkBasicHeader_t {
    uintn_t fmt                      :2; // format
    uintn_t provisionalChunkStreamID :6;
    if (provisionalChunkStreamID >= 2)
        chunkStreamID = provisionalChunkStreamID; // one-byte form
    else
    {
        if (0 == provisionalChunkStreamID)
            uint8_t chunkStreamIDMinus64; // two-byte form
        else // 1 == provisionalChunkStreamID
            uint16le_t chunkStreamIDMinus64; // three-byte form
        chunkStreamID = chunkStreamIDMinus64 + 64;
    }
} :variable*8;
]]></artwork>

<t>The <tt>chunkStreamIDMinus64</tt> field of the 3-byte form encodes the
chunk stream ID less 64 in little-endian byte order.</t>

</section> <!-- Chunk Basic Header -->

<section title="Chunk Message Header">

<t><xref target="RTMP" section="5.3.1.2" relative="#5312-chunk-message-header" sectionFormat="of"/>
describes the four Chunk Message Header formats. The format being used is
indicated by the <tt>fmt</tt> field of the Chunk Basic Header.</t>

<t>The <tt>Type 0</tt> Chunk Message Header format includes the RTMP Message
Stream ID. The description of the <tt>Message Stream ID (4 bytes)</tt> field
in
<xref target="RTMP" section="5.3.1.2.5" relative="#53125-common-header-fields" sectionFormat="of"/>
specifies that the field "is stored in little-endian format". However, the
diagram doesn't show this and it is easily missed. This section clarifies the
<tt>Type 0</tt> Chunk Message Header format.</t>

<artwork align="left" type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7|0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7|0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7|0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|               provisional timestamp           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                  message length               |message type id|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                     message stream id (LE)                    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+
|    if(0xFFFFFF == provisionalTimestamp)  extendedTimestamp    |
+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+

struct chunkMessageHeaderType0_t {
    uint24_t   provisionalTimestamp;
    uint24_t   messageLength;
    uint8_t    messageTypeID;
    uint32le_t messageStreamID;

    if (0xFFFFFF == provisionalTimestamp)
    {
        uint32_t extendedTimestamp;
        timestamp = extendedTimestamp;
    }
    else
        timestamp = provisionalTimestamp;
} :variable*8;
]]></artwork>

<t>The <tt>messageStreamID</tt> field encodes the message stream ID
as four bytes in little-endian byte order. Note however that
per <xref target="rtmp-message-format"/>
the message stream ID <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> exceed 16777215.</t>

</section> <!-- Chunk Message Header -->
</section> <!-- Byte Order -->

<section title="Timestamps">

<section title="Chunk Message Header Extended Timestamp">

<t><xref target="RTMP" section="5.3.1.2" relative="#5312-chunk-message-header" sectionFormat="of"/>
implies that the <tt>Extended Timestamp</tt> field is separate from the Chunk
Message Header. This implication is misleading because, when it is present,
it is in fact part of the chunk header and does not count toward the chunk's
payload or the <tt>Message Length</tt>. Because of this, all four types of
Chunk Message Header should be recognized as being variable-length.</t>

<t>While 
<xref target="RTMP" section="5.3.1.3" relative="#5313-extended-timestamp" sectionFormat="of"/>
states that the <tt>Extended Timestamp</tt> is present in <tt>Type 3</tt>
chunks when the most recent <tt>Type 0</tt>, <tt>Type 1</tt>, or <tt>Type
2</tt> chunk on the same Chunk Stream ID indicated the presence of an extended
timestamp, this has caused confusion for some implementors for the <tt>Type
3</tt> chunks that are the subsequent portions of the same message, or that
are the first chunk of subsequent messages on the same Chunk Stream ID. To
clarify: while the <tt>Extended Timestamp</tt> field is indicated, it
<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be present in <em>every</em> <tt>Type 3</tt> Chunk Message
Header for a message, including the first as well as subsequent chunks of
that message <em>and subsequent messages starting with <tt>Type 3</tt></em>,
even though this is wasteful.</t>

</section> <!-- Chunk Message Header Extended Timestamp -->

<section title="Timestamp Order of Messages">

<t><xref target="RTMP" section="5" relative="#5-rtmp-chunk-stream" sectionFormat="of"/>
states</t>

<blockquote>
When used with a reliable transport protocol such as TCP <xref target="RFC0793"/>,
RTMP Chunk Stream provides guaranteed timestamp-ordered end-to-end delivery
of all messages, across multiple streams.
</blockquote>

<t>However, this wording is misleading. For example,
<xref target="RTMP" section="5.3.1.2.1" relative="#53121type-0" sectionFormat="of"/>
alludes to a case where "the stream timestamp goes backward (e.g. because of
a backward seek)". Note that RTMP can be used for Video on Demand (VOD) and
Digital Video Recorder (DVR) playback as well as for live streaming.</t>

<t>Senders <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> apply real-time treatments to RTMP messages,
including prioritization policies and transmission deadlines. Prioritization
can include (but is not limited to) preferential allocation of transmission
resources to audio over video, or to one stream over another.  Prioritization
can cause, for example, later audio messages to be transmitted before earlier
video messages.</t>

<t>Senders have full control over scheduling, interleaving, and transmitting
RTMP messages, or portions thereof, over lower-layer transports. When using
RTMP Chunk Stream over a reliable, in-order transport protocol such as TCP
<xref target="RFC0793"/>, a sender can ensure delivery of messages in any
desired order, including in timestamp order.</t>

<t>For optimum interoperability with straightforward implementations and with
many existing implementations, timestamps <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> go backwards
in the same Message Stream ID for the same RTMP Message Type ID without an
explicit signal from the receiver (such as initiating a backward seek)
indicating such a jump is expected.</t>

</section> <!-- Timestamp Ordering of Messages -->

</section> <!-- Timestamps -->

<section title="Abandoning a Message">

<t><xref target="RTMP" section="5.4.2" relative="#542abort-message-2" sectionFormat="of"/>
describes the <tt>Abort Message</tt> Protocol Control Message. The description
of this message states</t>

<blockquote>
An application may send this message when closing in order to indicate that
further processing of the messages is not required.
</blockquote>

<t>This description is misleading, and suggests that receipt of this message
signals that no further processing of any messages is required, which is
incorrect.</t>

<t>This protocol control message aborts a single partially-transmitted message
on the indicated Chunk Stream ID. Afterward, new messages can commence on the
same Chunk Stream ID.</t>

<t>Senders can apply real-time treatments to messages, including transmission
deadlines. A message's transmission deadline might be exceeded after transmission
has started but before transmission is complete. Therefore, receivers
<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be operable to process the <tt>Abort Message</tt>
Protocol Control Message by discarding the partially-received message and
being prepared to receive a new message on the indicated Chunk Stream ID.</t>

<t>If at least one chunk for a new message is transmitted, then a timestamp
is established for that message against which a timestamp delta in a subsequent
message can be applied, even if the first message is aborted.</t>

</section> <!-- Abandoning a Message -->

<section title="RTMP Message Format" anchor="rtmp-message-format">

<t><xref target="RTMP" section="6.1" relative="#61-rtmp-message-format" sectionFormat="of"/>
defines the RTMP Message Format, with an explicit encoding of the RTMP message
header including field widths and byte ordering. However, this definition is
misleading because RTMP messages are not serialized according to this format
over either of the common transports. For example, when RTMP messages are
transported by the RTMP Chunk Stream, RTMP message headers are encoded into
Chunk Message Headers; and when RTMP messages are transported in RTMFP according
to <xref target="RFC7425" section="5.1" sectionFormat="of"/>, RTMP message
headers are encoded into flow metadata and the leading bytes of flow user
messages.  Therefore, the Message Header of the RTMP Message Format
<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be construed as a <em>virtual</em> or <em>semantic</em>
header that is mapped to the facilities of a lower-layer transport protocol
such as RTMP Chunk Stream or RTMFP.</t>

<t>The semantics of the RTMP Message Virtual Header and the encodings used in
the common transport protocols constrain the possible values of RTMP Message
Header fields. In particular:</t>

<ul>
	<li>Message Type is constrained to values from 0 to 255 inclusive;</li>

	<li>Message payloads can be at most 16777215 bytes long;</li>

	<li>Timestamps range from 0 to 4294967295 and wrap around;</li>

	<li>Stream ID is constrained to values from 0 to 16777215 inclusive.</li>

</ul>

<t>Note that in some cases these constraints are more restrictive than the
facilities provided by lower-layer transports. For example, RTMP Chunk Stream
could encode a Stream ID up to 4294967295; RTMFP could encode a Stream ID of
any finite non-negative integer (though typical implementations are limited
to 2<sup>64</sup> - 1) and transport messages of unlimited length. However,
exceeding the limits enumerated above will impede interoperability and protocol
translation, so they <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be exceeded.</t>

<section title="Alternative Transports and Processing Possible">

<t>RTMP Chunk Stream is not the ony possible transport service for RTMP
Messages. This flexibility is stated in several places. For example:</t>

<blockquote>
The [sic] section specifies the format of RTMP messages that are transferred between
entities on a network using a lower level transport layer, such as RTMP Chunk
Stream. While RTMP was designed to work with the RTMP Chunk Stream, it can
send the messages using any other transport protocol.
(<xref target="RTMP" section="6" relative="#6-rtmp-message-formats" sectionFormat="of"/>)
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
Real-time streaming network communication for the Flash platform of video,
audio, and data typically uses Adobe's Real-Time Messaging Protocol (RTMP)
messages.  RTMP messages were originally designed to be transported over RTMP
Chunk Stream in TCP; however, other transports (such as the one described in
this memo) are possible. (<xref target="RFC7425" section="1"/>)
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
The Flash platform uses RTMP messages for media streaming and communication.
This section describes how to transport RTMP messages over RTMFP flows and
additional messages and semantics unique to this transport.
(<xref target="RFC7425" section="5"/>)
</blockquote>

<t>This flexibility is memorialized here.</t>

<t>Note well that during ordinary processing, RTMP Messages can be translated
between different protocols and can pass through heterogeneous processing
elements, which can mask, confound, or destroy message meta-information beyond
the Message Virtual Header (such as the Chunk Stream ID or RTMFP flow on which
a message originally arrived).  Different processing elements can apply
different treatments, policies, priorities, and deadlines to RTMP message
streams, potentially affecting message arrival, arrival order, and interarrival
timing.</t>

</section> <!-- Alternative Transports Possible -->

<section title="Object Encoding 3" anchor="object-encoding-3">

<t>When <tt>objectEncoding</tt> 3 is negotiated during <tt>connect</tt>
(<xref target="object-encoding-negotiation"/>), <tt>Type 17</tt> Command
Extended and <tt>Type 15</tt> Data Extended messages can be used to carry
<xref target="AMF3">AMF 3</xref> coded values.</t>

<t><xref target="RTMP" section="7.1.1" relative="#711command-message-20-17" sectionFormat="of"/>
implies that a <tt>Type 17</tt> Command Extended message is a sequence of
AMF 3 coded values. Likewise,
<xref target="RTMP" section="7.1.2" relative="#712data-message-18-15" sectionFormat="of"/>
implies that a <tt>Type 15</tt> Data Extended message is a sequence of AMF 3
coded values. These implications are incorrect.</t>

<artwork align="left" type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|format selector|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+
|                          coded value                          |
+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+
                                :
+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+
|                          coded value                          |
+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+~+

// Message Type 17 "Command Extended" and Type 15 "Data Extended"
struct extendedActionMessagePayload_t {
    uint8_t formatSelector;

    if (0 == formatSelector)
    {
        while (remainder() > 0)
        {
            provisionalValue = decode_amf0();
            if (avmplus_object_marker == provisionalValue)
                // saw marker byte 0x11
                codedValue = decode_amf3();
            else
                codedValue = provisionalValue;
        }
    }
    // else unknown format
};
]]></artwork>

<t>A <tt>Type 17</tt> Command Extended or <tt>Type 15</tt> Data Extended
message payload begins with a format selector byte, followed by a sequence
of values in a format-specific encoding.  Currently only format 0 is defined;
therefore, the format selector byte <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 0.  Format 0 is a
sequence of AMF values, each encoded in AMF 0 by default; AMF 3 encoding for
a value is selected by prefixing it with an <tt>avmplus-object-marker</tt>
(byte <tt>0x11</tt>) as defined in <xref target="AMF0"/>.</t>

<t><tt>Type 20</tt> Command messages and <tt>Type 18</tt> Data messages
comprise a sequence of AMF 0 coded values, as originally implied.</t>

</section> <!-- Object Encoding 3 -->

</section> <!-- RTMP Message Format -->

<section title="Remote Procedure Call">

<section title="connect" anchor="connect-message">

<t><xref target="RTMP" section="7.2.1.1" relative="#7211connect" sectionFormat="of"/>
lists parameters for the <tt>connect</tt> command and their potential values
or ranges. However, this section contains incomplete and misleading information
particularly in capability negotiation.</t>

<section title="objectEncoding Negotiation" anchor="object-encoding-negotiation">

<t>The <tt>objectEncoding</tt> member of the <tt>connect</tt> Command Object
is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> with a default value of 0. If given, the possible
values are 0 and 3 (Numbers). This value indicates the Object Encoding methods
supported by the client. A value of 0 indicates support only for AMF 0 and
the <tt>Type 20</tt> Command and <tt>Type 18</tt> Data message types.  A
value of 3 indicates support for both AMF 0 and AMF 3, and for <tt>Type 17</tt>
Command Extended and <tt>Type 15</tt> Data Extended messages in addition to
<tt>Type 20</tt> and <tt>Type 18</tt> messages. See
<xref target="object-encoding-3"/> for the corrected encoding of these
message types.</t>

<t>The server responds with the highest legal value that both it and the
client support (that is, the server <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> send <tt>3</tt>
if the client didn't send <tt>3</tt>). Some clients require this member in
the <tt>_result</tt>, so the server <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> send it. If Object
Encoding 0 is negotiated, client and server <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> send
Command Extended or Data Extended messages to each other. If Object Encoding
3 is negotiated, client and server can use either the normal (<tt>Type 20</tt>
and <tt>Type 18</tt>) or extended (<tt>Type 17</tt> and <tt>Type 15</tt>)
message types at any time.</t>

</section> <!-- objectEncoding Negotiation -->

<section title="tcUrl">

<t>The <tt>tcUrl</tt> member of the <tt>connect</tt> Command Object
is <bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>. Its value is a string representing the URI
to which the client is connecting. Contrary to
<xref target="RTMP" section="7.2.1.1" relative="#7211connect" sectionFormat="of"/>,
RTMP family URIs follow the
<xref target="RFC3986">generic syntax for URIs</xref>. The interpretation
of any path or query components of the URI is reserved for the server.
Note that per <xref target="security-considerations">Security Considerations</xref>,
the client <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> strip any <tt>userinfo</tt> and <tt>fragment</tt>
components from the URI before sending it.</t>

<t>Interoperability Note: Some clients interpret and rewrite the <tt>path</tt>
component of the URI, using one or more <tt>segment</tt>s of the path for a
non-connection purpose such as the name of a stream to play or publish. This
behavior is not interoperable and is <bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>. A
recommendation of an alternative is beyond the purview of this memo; however,
the community might consider more semantically appropriate alternatives, for
example using the <tt>fragment</tt> component to indicate client-side parameters
and behaviors such as the name of a stream to play or publish.</t>

</section> <!-- tcUrl -->

<section title="app">

<t>The <tt>app</tt> member of the <tt>connect</tt> Command Object
is <bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>. Its value is a string indicating the
<em>application instance</em> to which the client is connecting. Its value
is usually the path component of the URI to which the client is connecting,
not including the leading slash (if any). However, this is not required;
clients <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> set <tt>app</tt> to a different value if appropriate.
The interpretation of <tt>app</tt> and the meaning of "application instance"
is reserved for the server.</t>

</section> <!-- app -->

<section title="Codec Negotiation">

<t>The <tt>videoCodecs</tt> and <tt>audioCodecs</tt> members of the
<tt>connect</tt> Command Object are bit fields representing the video and
audio codecs, respectively, that the client is capable and willing to receive.
These members are <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> and each defaults to 0 (that is,
no bits set, so no codecs indicated). The values for these fields are
enumerated in
<xref target="RTMP" section="7.2.1.1" relative="#7211connect" sectionFormat="of"/>;
multiple codecs are combined with bitwise-or.</t>

<t>Interoperability Note: Some server implementations, including Adobe Media
Server, use this information to selectively filter out <tt>Video</tt> and
<tt>Audio</tt> messages having codecs not indicated in the respective bit
fields. In other words, some servers might not send the video and/or audio
messages of certain streams unless these members are sent with appropriate
values. Therefore, clients <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> send <tt>videoCodecs</tt>
and <tt>audioCodecs</tt> in the <tt>connect</tt> command indicating at least
their supported playback codecs.</t>

</section> <!-- Codec Negotiation -->

</section> <!-- connect -->

<section title="call">

<t><xref target="RTMP" section="7.2.1.2" relative="#7212call" sectionFormat="of"/>,
in context, conflates the <tt>call</tt> method on a <tt>NetConnection</tt>
ActionScript object (specific to Flash Player and Adobe Integrated Runtime)
with the encoding of a Remote Procedure Call into an RTMP Command message.
This is misleading.  However, the command structure illustrated in that section
is correct. The name of the remote procedure to invoke on the peer is given
as the first field, and the string "<tt>call</tt>" does not appear in the
command message sent to the peer.</t>

</section> <!-- call -->

<section title="deleteStream">

<t><xref target="RTMP" section="7.2.2.3" relative="#7223deletestream" sectionFormat="of"/>
erroneously states that the <tt>deleteStream</tt> command is a <em>stream</em>
command. The <tt>deleteStream</tt> command is actually a <em>connection</em>
command and is to be sent on Message Stream ID 0. The Message Stream ID being
deleted is sent as the fourth field of the command message, as indicated.</t>

</section> <!-- deleteStream -->

</section> <!-- Remote Procedure Call -->

<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>This memo has no IANA actions.</t>
</section> <!-- IANA -->

<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security-considerations">

<t>RTMP and RTMFP URIs use the <xref target="RFC3986">generic syntax for
URIs</xref>.  URIs can encode sensitive or private information such as user
names, passwords, stream names, and so on. Implementations <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
remove any <tt>userinfo</tt> and <tt>fragment</tt> components of a URI before
sending it as the <tt>tcUrl</tt> member of the <tt>connect</tt> command's
Command Object or in the Ancillary Data option of an RTMFP Endpoint Discriminator
(<xref target="RFC7425" section="4.4.2.2" sectionFormat="of"/>).</t>

</section> <!-- Security Considerations -->

</middle>

<back>
	<references>
	<name>References</name>

	<references title="Normative References">

		<reference anchor="AMF0" target="https://rtmp.veriskope.com/pdf/amf0-file-format-specification.pdf">
			<front>
				<title>Action Message Format -- AMF 0</title>
				<author><organization>Adobe Inc.</organization></author>
				<date month="December" year="2007"/>
			</front>
		</reference>

		<reference anchor="AMF3" target="https://rtmp.veriskope.com/pdf/amf3-file-format-spec.pdf">
			<front>
				<title>Action Message Format -- AMF 3</title>
				<author><organization>Adobe Inc.</organization></author>
				<date month="January" year="2013"/>
			</front>
		</reference>

		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/> <!-- BCP14 -->
		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml"/> <!-- URI syntax -->
		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7016.xml"/> <!-- RTMFP -->
		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7425.xml"/> <!-- RTMP in RTMFP -->
		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/> <!-- BCP14 -->

		<reference anchor="RTMP" target="https://rtmp.veriskope.com/docs/spec/">
			<front>
				<title>Adobe’s Real Time Messaging Protocol</title>
				<author initials="H." surname="Parmar" role="editor"/>
				<author initials="M." surname="Thornburgh" role="editor"/>
				<date month="December" year="2012"/>
			</front>
		</reference>

	</references>

	<references title="Informative References">

		<reference anchor="E-RTMP" target="https://github.com/veovera/enhanced-rtmp/blob/main/enhanced-rtmp-v1.pdf">
			<front>
				<title>Enhancing RTMP, FLV With Additional Video Codecs and HDR Support</title>
				<author initials="S." surname="Lozben"/>
				<date month="March" year="2023"/>
			</front>
		</reference>

		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0793.xml"/> <!-- TCP -->

	</references>

	</references>
</back>

</rfc>
