<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc7991.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="none" submissionType="independent" category="info" version="3">

<front>
	<title abbrev="RTMP URIs">RTMP Family URI Schemes</title>

	<author initials="M." surname="Thornburgh" fullname="Michael C. Thornburgh">
		<address>
			<postal>
				<city>Santa Cruz</city>
				<region>CA</region>
				<code>95060-1950</code>
				<country>US</country>
			</postal>
			<email>zenomt@zenomt.com</email>
			<uri>https://zenomt.zenomt.com/card#me</uri>
		</address>
	</author>

	<abstract><t>

		Adobe’s Real-Time Messaging Protocol (RTMP) comprises a family
		of network protocols for transporting streams of time-oriented
		video, audio, and data messages over IP networks.  The URI
		schemes that are used to identify, locate, and access streaming
		resources in the RTMP family follow the URI Generic Syntax
		of RFC 3986, with constraints.  This memo describes the syntax
		constraints and the access semantics for RTMP family URIs.

	</t></abstract>

	<note>
		<name>Copyright Notice</name>

		<t>Copyright © 2023 Michael Thornburgh. All rights reserved.</t>

		<t>Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person
		obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation
		files (the "Software"), to deal in the Software without
		restriction, including without limitation the rights to use,
		copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or
		sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom
		the Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following
		conditions:</t>

		<t>The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall
		be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
		Software.</t>

		<t>THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY
		KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE
		WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE
		AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT
		HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY,
		WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
		FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE
		OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.</t>

	</note>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

<t>Adobe’s Real-Time Messaging Protocol (RTMP) comprises a family of network
protocols for transporting streams of time-oriented video, audio, and data
messages over IP networks.</t>

<t>The URI schemes that are used to identify, locate, and access streaming
resources in the RTMP family follow the URI Generic Syntax of
<xref target="RFC3986"/>, with constraints.</t>

<t>
RTMP and its TCP-based transport (the RTMP Chunk Stream) are described in the
<xref target="RTMP">RTMP Specification of December 2012</xref>. Errors,
omissions, and ambiguities in that specification are addressed in
<xref target="RTMP-Errata">RTMP Errata and Addenda</xref>.  Coordinated interoperable
enhancements to RTMP are described in
<xref target="E-RTMP">Enhanced RTMP</xref>. Transporting RTMP messages over the
<xref target="RFC7016">Secure Real-Time Media Flow Protocol (RTMFP)</xref>
is described in
<xref target="RFC7425">Adobe's RTMFP Profile for Flash Communication</xref>.
</t>

<t>This memo describes the syntax constraints and the access semantics for
RTMP family URIs.</t>

<t>This memo does not address private or undocumented extensions to the RTMP
family for which interoperation is not desired by the extending parties.</t>

<t>The primary operation for dereferencing an RTMP family URI is to connect
to the indicated origin server and its abstract <em>target resource</em>.
Neither the connection itself nor the target resource have a "representation"
or a "media type" in the senses described in RFC 3986, nor is a "retrieval"
performed by connecting.</t>

<t>The target resource can have secondary resources, such as streams, shared
objects, and remote procedures, that can be accessed according their kinds
via the connection. For example, streams may be published or played, shared
objects updated or observed, and remote procedures called.</t>

</section> <!-- Introduction -->

<section title="Terminology">

<t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
"<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
"<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
"<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>"
in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
<xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they
appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

<t>The terms "client", "server", "origin server", "resource", "secondary
resource", "dereference", "representation", and "media type" in this document
are to be interpreted as used or described in <xref target="RFC3986"/>.</t>

</section> <!-- Terminology -->

<section title="Syntax">

<t>RTMP family URIs follow the Generic Syntax of <xref target="RFC3986"/>,
with constraints.  Their syntax is described here using the
<xref target="RFC5234">Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF)</xref> rules from
RFC 3986, which are incorporated by reference as though fully set forth here.
The <tt>host</tt> rule is also reproduced here for clarity in the following
sections.  Note that the <tt>rtmp-authority</tt> rule defined here is compatible
with the <tt>authority</tt> rule, and <tt>rtmp-userinfo</tt> is compatible
with the <tt>userinfo</tt> rule.</t>

<sourcecode><![CDATA[
rtmp-URI  = "rtmp://" common

rtmps-URI = "rtmps://" common

rtmfp-URI = "rtmfp:" ["//" common]

common = rtmp-authority path-abempty ["?" query] ["#" fragment]

rtmp-authority   = [rtmp-userinfo "@"] host [":" port]

rtmp-userinfo    = rtmp-connect-arg *(":" rtmp-connect-arg)

rtmp-connect-arg = *(unreserved / pct-encoded / sub-delims)

host = IP-literal / IPv4address / reg-name
]]></sourcecode>

</section> <!-- Syntax -->

<section title="Authority">

<t>The <tt>rtmp-authority</tt> component, when present, identifies the location
of an RTMP origin server which governs a namespace of target and secondary
resources.</t>

<t>Note: The bare RTMFP URI form "<tt>rtmfp:</tt>" does not have an
<tt>rtmp-authority</tt> component (or any other components).  All of the other
URI forms do. The bare "<tt>rtmfp:</tt>" URI is used in the APIs of some
implementations to indicate instantiation of an RTMFP client according to
<xref target="RFC7425"/>, but without connecting to a server.  Such an
instantiation might be used for pure peer-to-peer communication.</t>

<section title="Host and Port">

<t> The <tt>host</tt> and optional <tt>port</tt> components locate the origin
server in the network. The <tt>host</tt> component of the <tt>rtmp-authority</tt>
<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be empty.</t>

<t>For an <tt>rtmp-URI</tt>, the <tt>host</tt> and optional <tt>port</tt>
identify a potential origin server listening for <xref target="RFC0793">TCP</xref>
connections, over which RTMP messages are to be sent using the RTMP Chunk
Stream as described in the <xref target="RTMP">RTMP Specification</xref>.  If
the <tt>port</tt> is empty or not given, TCP port <tt>1935</tt> is the
default.</t>

<t>For an <tt>rtmps-URI</tt>, the <tt>host</tt> and optional <tt>port</tt>
identify a potential origin server listening for TCP connections and capable
of establishing a <xref target="RFC8446">TLS</xref> connection secured for
<xref target="RTMP">RTMP Chunk Stream communication</xref>. "Secured" means
a connection that is authenticated, confidential, and integrity-protected in
a manner acceptable to both the client and server.  If the <tt>port</tt> is
empty or not given, TCP port <tt>443</tt> is the default.</t>

<t>For an <tt>rtmfp-URI</tt> where the <tt>rtmp-authority</tt> is present,
the <tt>host</tt> and optional <tt>port</tt> identify one or more initial
candidate addresses with which to initiate an <xref target="RFC7016">RTMFP</xref>
connection according to <xref target="RFC7425"/>.  The
<xref target="RFC0768">UDP</xref> port for the initial candidate addresses,
if empty or not specified, is <tt>1935</tt>.  If <tt>host</tt> is a
<tt>reg-name</tt>, the initial candidate address set <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
comprise all IPv4 and IPv6 addresses to which <tt>reg-name</tt> resolves.</t>

</section> <!-- Host and Port -->

<section title="Userinfo">

<t>When connecting to an RTMP server, the <tt>connect</tt> command
(Section 7.2.1.1 of <xref target="RTMP"/>) can accept or expect additional
arguments following the <em>Command Object</em>. The number and types of the
additional arguments, their interpretation, and whether they are expected is
implementation-specific and is the prerogative of the server.</t>

<t>Often the server expects one or more string arguments to the <tt>connect</tt>
command following the <em>Command Object</em>, for example a developer key,
a user name and password, or implementation-specific connection properties.</t>

<t>If the <tt>rtmp-authority</tt> contains an <tt>rtmp-userinfo</tt> component,
and in the absence of other arrangements between the client and server, the
<tt>rtmp-userinfo</tt> <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be interpreted as a "<tt>:</tt>"
(<tt>COLON</tt>) separated sequence of potentially empty <tt>rtmp-connect-arg</tt>
strings (as illustrated in the ABNF) to be sent as string arguments to the
<tt>connect</tt> command following the <em>Command Object</em>. Each
<tt>rtmp-connect-arg</tt> <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be percent-decoded before
being sent.</t>

<t>Clients <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> remove the <tt>rtmp-userinfo</tt> component
from the URI when sending it as the <tt>tcUrl</tt> property of the <tt>connect</tt>
command’s <em>Command Object</em> or in the Ancillary Data option of an RTMFP Endpoint Discriminator
(<xref target="RFC7425" section="4.4.2.2" sectionFormat="of"/>).</t>

</section> <!-- Userinfo -->
</section> <!-- Authority -->

<section title="Path and Query">

<t>The <tt>path-abempty</tt> and <tt>query</tt> components identify the
abstract <em>target resource</em> within the origin server’s namespace. The
meaning of "target resource" is implementation-specific and is the prerogative
of the origin server.</t>

<t>Interoperability Note: Some client implementations incorrectly presume the
server’s interpretation of the <tt>path-abempty</tt> component of the URI,
specifically by presuming the number of path segments that identify the target
resource. These clients then incorrectly interpret the remaining path segments
of the original URI as identifying a secondary resource (such as the name of
a stream to play or publish via the connection to the target resource).  This
behavior is not in keeping with the spirit of URIs (particularly that the
<tt>authority</tt> governs its namespace), is not interoperable, and is
<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>. Such secondary resources, when encoded in a
URI, should instead be identified by the fragment identifier as described in
the next section.</t>

</section> <!-- Path and Query -->

<section title="Fragment Identifier">

<t><xref target="RFC3986" section="3.5" sectionFormat="of"/> describes the
<tt>fragment</tt> component of a generic URI as allowing "indirect identification
of a secondary resource by reference to a primary resource and additional
identifying information".</t>

<t>Since an RTMP connection to a target resource has neither a "representation"
nor a "media type", the semantics of the <tt>fragment</tt> component are
unconstrained according to that section.</t>

<t>Often an RTMP client connects to a server to perform a specific operation
on a specific secondary resource, such as to publish to or play from a named
stream.  In cases where the kind of secondary resource and the intended
operation are unambiguous, and in the absence of other arrangements between
the client and server, the secondary resource <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be identified
by the <tt>fragment</tt> component. The <tt>fragment</tt> <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
be percent-decoded before being used in secondary resource APIs (for example
in a stream <tt>play</tt> command).</t>

<t>Clients <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> remove the <tt>fragment</tt> component from
the URI when sending it as the <tt>tcUrl</tt> property of the <tt>connect</tt>
command’s <em>Command Object</em> or in the Ancillary Data option of an RTMFP
Endpoint Discriminator
(<xref target="RFC7425" section="4.4.2.2" sectionFormat="of"/>).</t>

</section> <!-- Fragment Identifier -->

<section title="Examples">

<sourcecode><![CDATA[
rtmp://server.example/three/segment/path
rtmp://server.example/three/segment/path#BigBuckBunny
rtmp://[2001:db8:1::2]:19350/something?else

rtmps://server.example/something?else#CosmosLaundromat?aFlag
rtmps://arg1:arg2::arg4@server.example:1943
rtmps://name=Mike;pri=5;exi=3600:7c412a7b6e@server.example/path#Caves

rtmfp://:arg2@redirectors.example/two/segments?key=value&flag
rtmfp://arg%3Aone:arg2@redirectors.example/something#BigBuck%42unny
rtmfp:
]]></sourcecode>

</section> <!-- Examples -->

<section title="IANA Considerations">

<t>A future version of this memo will request of the IANA to update the
<xref target="SCHEMES">URI Scheme Registry</xref> for the following schemes.</t>

<section title="RTMP Registration">

<t>This section will request an update to the <tt>rtmp</tt> provisional scheme
registration.</t>

<dl>
	<dt>Scheme Name:</dt>
	<dd><tt>rtmp</tt></dd>

	<dt>Status:</dt>
	<dd>provisional</dd>

	<dt>URI scheme syntax:</dt>
	<dd><sourcecode><![CDATA[
rtmp-URI = "rtmp://" common

common = rtmp-authority path-abempty ["?" query] ["#" fragment]

rtmp-authority   = [rtmp-userinfo "@"] host [":" port]

rtmp-userinfo    = rtmp-connect-arg *(":" rtmp-connect-arg)

rtmp-connect-arg = *(unreserved / pct-encoded / sub-delims)
	]]></sourcecode></dd>

	<dt>URI scheme semantics:</dt>
	<dd>
		<t>This provides location information for the RTMP server to
		which to connect, and identifies a target resource and an
		optional secondary resource in the namespace of the server.
		The host component of the authority <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>
		be empty.  The host and optional port components of the
		authority identify a potential origin server listening for
		TCP connections, over which RTMP messages are to be sent using
		the RTMP Chunk Stream as described in the RTMP Specification
		(as amended).  If port is empty or not given, TCP port 1935
		is the default.</t>

		<t>See the RTMP Family URI Schemes memo for more specific
		information regarding the semantics of this URI scheme.</t>
	</dd>

	<dt>Encoding considerations:</dt>
	<dd>The <tt>rtmp-userinfo</tt>, <tt>path-abempty</tt>, <tt>query</tt>,
	and <tt>fragment</tt> components represent textual data consisting
	of characters from the Universal Character Set. These components
	<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be encoded according to Section 2.5 of RFC
	3986.</dd>

	<dt>Applications/protocols that use this URI scheme name:</dt>
	<dd>Computer program products that use Adobe's Real-Time Messaging
	Protocol (RTMP) to transport streams of time-oriented video, audio,
	and data messages over IP networks.</dd>

	<dt>Interoperability considerations:</dt>
	<dd>This scheme requires use of RTMP and the RTMP Chunk Stream as
	defined by the RTMP Specification (as amended).</dd>

	<dt>Security considerations:</dt>
	<dd>See the Security Considerations sections in RTMP Errata and Addenda
	and in RTMP Family URI Schemes.</dd>

	<dt>Contact:</dt>
	<dd>Michael Thornburgh, <tt>&lt;zenomt@zenomt.com&gt;</tt>.</dd>

	<dt>Author/Change controller:</dt>
	<dd>Michael Thornburgh, <tt>&lt;zenomt@zenomt.com&gt;</tt>.</dd>

	<dt>References:</dt>
	<dd>
		<t>Parmar, H., Ed. and M. Thornburgh, Ed., "Adobe’s Real Time
		Messaging Protocol" ("RTMP Specification"), December 2012,
		<tt>&lt;https://veovera.org/docs/legacy/rtmp-v1-0-spec.pdf&gt;</tt>.</t>

		<t>Thornburgh, M., "RTMP Errata and Addenda", July 2024,
		<tt>&lt;https://zenomt.github.io/rtmp-errata-addenda/&gt;</tt>.</t>

		<t>Thornburgh, M., "RTMP Family URI Schemes", July 2024,
		<tt>&lt;https://zenomt.github.io/rtmp-errata-addenda/rtmp-uris/&gt;</tt>.</t>

		<t>Lozben, S., "Enhanced RTMP", June 2024, <tt>&lt;https://veovera.org/&gt;</tt>.</t>
	</dd>

</dl>

</section> <!-- RTMP Registration-->

<section title="RTMPS Registration">

<t>This section will request provisional registration of the <tt>rtmps</tt> scheme.</t>

<dl>
	<dt>Scheme Name:</dt>
	<dd><tt>rtmps</tt></dd>

	<dt>Status:</dt>
	<dd>provisional</dd>

	<dt>URI scheme syntax:</dt>
	<dd><sourcecode><![CDATA[
rtmps-URI = "rtmps://" common

common = rtmp-authority path-abempty ["?" query] ["#" fragment]

rtmp-authority   = [rtmp-userinfo "@"] host [":" port]

rtmp-userinfo    = rtmp-connect-arg *(":" rtmp-connect-arg)

rtmp-connect-arg = *(unreserved / pct-encoded / sub-delims)
	]]></sourcecode></dd>

	<dt>URI scheme semantics:</dt>
	<dd>
		<t>This provides location information for the secure RTMP
		server to which to connect, and identifies a target resource
		and an optional secondary resource in the namespace of the
		server.  The host component of the authority <bcp14>MUST
		NOT</bcp14> be empty.  The host and optional port components
		of the authority identify a potential origin server listening
		for TCP connections and capable of establishing a TLS connection
		secured for RTMP Chunk Stream communication, over which RTMP
		messages are to be sent using the RTMP Chunk Stream as described
		in the RTMP Specification (as amended).  If port is empty or
		not given, TCP port 443 is the default.</t>

		<t>See the RTMP Family URI Schemes memo for more specific
		information regarding the semantics of this URI scheme.</t>
	</dd>

	<dt>Encoding considerations:</dt>
	<dd>The <tt>rtmp-userinfo</tt>, <tt>path-abempty</tt>, <tt>query</tt>,
	and <tt>fragment</tt> components represent textual data consisting
	of characters from the Universal Character Set. These components
	<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be encoded according to Section 2.5 of RFC
	3986.</dd>

	<dt>Applications/protocols that use this URI scheme name:</dt>
	<dd>Computer program products that use Adobe's Real-Time Messaging
	Protocol (RTMP) to securely transport streams of time-oriented video,
	audio, and data messages over IP networks.</dd>

	<dt>Interoperability considerations:</dt>
	<dd>This scheme requires use of RTMP and the RTMP Chunk Stream as
	defined by the RTMP Specification (as amended) over TLS.</dd>

	<dt>Security considerations:</dt>
	<dd>See the Security Considerations sections in RTMP Errata and Addenda
	and in RTMP Family URI Schemes.</dd>

	<dt>Contact:</dt>
	<dd>Michael Thornburgh, <tt>&lt;zenomt@zenomt.com&gt;</tt>.</dd>

	<dt>Author/Change controller:</dt>
	<dd>Michael Thornburgh, <tt>&lt;zenomt@zenomt.com&gt;</tt>.</dd>

	<dt>References:</dt>
	<dd>
		<t>Parmar, H., Ed. and M. Thornburgh, Ed., "Adobe’s Real Time
		Messaging Protocol" ("RTMP Specification"), December 2012,
		<tt>&lt;https://veovera.org/docs/legacy/rtmp-v1-0-spec.pdf&gt;</tt>.</t>

		<t>Thornburgh, M., "RTMP Errata and Addenda", July 2024,
		<tt>&lt;https://zenomt.github.io/rtmp-errata-addenda/&gt;</tt>.</t>

		<t>Thornburgh, M., "RTMP Family URI Schemes", July 2024,
		<tt>&lt;https://zenomt.github.io/rtmp-errata-addenda/rtmp-uris/&gt;</tt>.</t>

		<t>Lozben, S., "Enhanced RTMP", June 2024, <tt>&lt;https://veovera.org/&gt;</tt>.</t>
	</dd>

</dl>

</section> <!-- RTMPS Registration-->

<section title="RTMFP Registration">

<t>This section will request an update to the <tt>rtmfp</tt> provisional scheme registration.</t>

<dl>
	<dt>Scheme Name:</dt>
	<dd><tt>rtmfp</tt></dd>

	<dt>Status:</dt>
	<dd>provisional</dd>

	<dt>URI scheme syntax:</dt>
	<dd><sourcecode><![CDATA[
rtmfp-URI = "rtmfp:" ["//" common]

common = rtmp-authority path-abempty ["?" query] ["#" fragment]

rtmp-authority   = [rtmp-userinfo "@"] host [":" port]

rtmp-userinfo    = rtmp-connect-arg *(":" rtmp-connect-arg)

rtmp-connect-arg = *(unreserved / pct-encoded / sub-delims)
	]]></sourcecode></dd>

	<dt>URI scheme semantics:</dt>
	<dd>
		<t>The scheme-only form is used in the APIs of some implementations
		to indicate instantiation of an RTMFP client according to RFC
		7425, but without connecting to a server.  Such an instantiation
		might be used for pure peer-to-peer communication.</t>

		<t>The full form provides location information for the RTMFP
		server to which to connect, and identifies a target resource
		and an optional secondary resource in the namespace of the
		server.  Connections are made using RTMFP (RFC 7016) as
		described by RFC 7425.  The host component of the authority
		<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be empty. If host is a <tt>reg-name</tt>,
		the initial candidate address set <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
		comprise all IPv4 and IPv6 addresses to which <tt>reg-name</tt>
		resolves.  The UDP port for the initial candidate addresses
		for the server, if not specified, is 1935.</t>

		<t>See the RTMP Family URI Schemes memo for more specific
		information regarding the semantics of this URI scheme.</t>
	</dd>

	<dt>Encoding considerations:</dt>
	<dd>The <tt>rtmp-userinfo</tt>, <tt>path-abempty</tt>, <tt>query</tt>,
	and <tt>fragment</tt> components represent textual data consisting
	of characters from the Universal Character Set. These components
	<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be encoded according to Section 2.5 of RFC
	3986.</dd>

	<dt>Applications/protocols that use this URI scheme name:</dt>
	<dd>Computer program products that use Adobe's Secure Real-Time Media
	Flow Protocol (RTMFP) according to RFC 7425 to transport streams of
	time-oriented video, audio, and data messages over IP networks.</dd>

	<dt>Interoperability considerations:</dt>
	<dd>This scheme requires use of RTMFP as defined by RFC 7016 in the
	manner described by RFC 7425.</dd>

	<dt>Security considerations:</dt>
	<dd>See the Security Considerations sections of RFC 7016, RFC 7425,
	and RTMP Errata and Addenda.</dd>

	<dt>Contact:</dt>
	<dd>Michael Thornburgh, <tt>&lt;zenomt@zenomt.com&gt;</tt>.</dd>

	<dt>Author/Change controller:</dt>
	<dd>Michael Thornburgh, <tt>&lt;zenomt@zenomt.com&gt;</tt>.</dd>

	<dt>References:</dt>
	<dd>
		<t>Thornburgh, M., "Adobe's Secure Real-Time Media Flow
		Protocol", RFC 7016, November 2013.</t>

		<t>Thornburgh, M., "Adobe's RTMFP Profile for Flash Communication",
		RFC 7425, December 2014.</t>

		<t>Thornburgh, M., "RTMP Errata and Addenda", July 2024,
		<tt>&lt;https://zenomt.github.io/rtmp-errata-addenda/&gt;</tt>.</t>

		<t>Thornburgh, M., "RTMP Family URI Schemes", July 2024,
		<tt>&lt;https://zenomt.github.io/rtmp-errata-addenda/rtmp-uris/&gt;</tt>.</t>
	</dd>

</dl>
</section> <!-- RTMFP Registration-->

</section> <!-- IANA Considerations -->

<section title="Security Considerations">

<t>Several. See the Security Considerations sections of <xref target="RFC7016"/>,
<xref target="RFC7425"/>, and <xref target="RTMP-Errata"/>.</t>

<t>Many of the security considerations of <xref target="RFC9110"/> also apply
to RTMP.</t>

</section> <!-- Security Considerations -->

</middle>

<back>
	<references>
	<name>References</name>

	<references title="Normative References">

		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0768.xml"/> <!-- UDP -->
		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0793.xml"/> <!-- TCP -->
		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/> <!-- BCP14 -->
		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml"/> <!-- URI syntax -->
		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml"/> <!-- ABNF -->
		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7016.xml"/> <!-- RTMFP -->
		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7425.xml"/> <!-- RTMP in RTMFP -->
		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/> <!-- BCP14 -->
		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"/> <!-- TLS -->

		<reference anchor="RTMP" target="https://veovera.org/docs/legacy/rtmp-v1-0-spec.pdf">
			<front>
				<title>Adobe’s Real Time Messaging Protocol</title>
				<author initials="H." surname="Parmar" role="editor"/>
				<author initials="M." surname="Thornburgh" role="editor"/>
				<date month="December" year="2012"/>
			</front>
		</reference>

	</references>

	<references title="Informative References">

		<reference anchor="E-RTMP" target="https://veovera.org/">
			<front>
				<title>Enhanced RTMP</title>
				<author initials="S." surname="Lozben"/>
				<date month="June" year="2024"/>
			</front>
		</reference>

		<xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9110.xml"/> <!-- HTTP -->

		<reference anchor="RTMP-Errata" target="https://zenomt.github.io/rtmp-errata-addenda/">
			<front>
				<title>RTMP Errata and Addenda</title>
				<author initials="M." surname="Thornburgh"/>
				<date month="July" year="2024"/>
			</front>
		</reference>

		<reference anchor="SCHEMES" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/uri-schemes/">
			<front>
				<title>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) Schemes</title>
				<author><organization>Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</organization></author>
			</front>
		</reference>

	</references>

	</references>
</back>

</rfc>
